<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="user-manual-intro">
    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>
        Welcome to the BitBake User Manual.
        This manual provides information on BitBake.
        The information attempts to be as independent as possible regarding
        systems that use BitBake, such as the Yocto Project and
        OpenEmbeddeded.
        In some cases, scenarios or examples that within the context of
        a build system are used in the manual to help with understanding.
        For these cases, the manual clearly states the context.
    </para>

    <section id="intro">
        <title>Introduction</title>

        <para>
            Fundamentally, BitBake is a generic task execution
            engine that allows shell and Python tasks to be run
            efficiently and in parallel while working within
            complex inter-task dependency constraints.
            One of BitBake's main users, OpenEmbedded, takes this core
            and builds embedded Linux software stacks using
            a task-oriented approach.
        </para>

        <para>
            Conceptually, BitBake is similar to GNU Make in
            some regards but has significant differences:
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem><para>
                    BitBake executes tasks according to provided
                    metadata that builds up the tasks.
                    Metadata is stored in recipe (<filename>.bb</filename>),
                    configuration (<filename>.conf</filename>), and class
                    (<filename>.bbclass</filename>) files and provides
                    BitBake with instructions on what tasks to run and
                    the dependencies between those tasks.
                    </para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>
                    BitBake includes a fetcher library for obtaining source
                    code from various places such as source control
                    systems or websites.
                    </para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>
                    The instructions for each unit to be built (e.g. a piece
                    of software) are known as recipe files and
                    contain all the information about the unit
                    (dependencies, source file locations, checksums, description
                    and so on).
                    </para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>
                    BitBake includes a client/server abstraction and can
                    be used from a command line or used as a service over XMLRPC and
                    has several different user interfaces.
                    </para></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
    </section>

    <section id="history-and-goals">
        <title>History and Goals</title>

        <para>
            BitBake was originally a part of the OpenEmbedded project.
            It was inspired by the Portage package management system
            used by the Gentoo Linux distribution.
            On December 7, 2004, OpenEmbedded project team member,
            Chris Larson split the project into two distinct pieces:
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem><para>BitBake, a generic task executor</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>OpenEmbedded, a metadata set utilized by
                    BitBake</para></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            Today, BitBake is the primary basis of the
            <ulink url="http://www.openembedded.org/">OpenEmbedded</ulink>
            project, which is being used to build and maintain Linux
            distributions such as the Angstrom Distribution and which is used
            as the build tool for Linux projects such as the Yocto Project.
        </para>

        <para>
            Prior to BitBake, no other build tool adequately met the needs of
            an aspiring embedded Linux distribution.
            All of the build systems used by traditional desktop Linux
            distributions lacked important functionality, and none of the
            ad-hoc buildroot systems, prevalent in the
            embedded space, were scalable or maintainable.
        </para>

        <para>
            Some important original goals for BitBake were:
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem><para>
                    Handle cross-compilation.
                    </para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>
                    Handle inter-package dependencies (build time on
                    target architecture, build time on native
                    architecture, and runtime).
                    </para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>
                    Support running any number of tasks within a given
                    package, including, but not limited to, fetching
                    upstream sources, unpacking them, patching them,
                    configuring them, and so forth.
                    </para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>
                    Be Linux distribution agnostic for both build and
                    target systems.
                    </para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>
                    Be architecture agnostic.
                    </para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>
                    Support multiple build and target operating systems
                    (e.g. Cygwin, the BSDs, and so forth).
                    </para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>
                    Be self contained, rather than tightly
                    integrated into the build machine's root
                    filesystem.
                    </para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>
                    Handle conditional metadata on the target architecture,
                    operating system, distribution, and machine.
                    </para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>
                    Be easy to use the tools to supply local metadata and packages
                    against which to operate.
                    </para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>
                    Be easy to use BitBake to collaborate between multiple
                    projects for their builds.
                    </para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>
                    Provide an inheritance mechanism that share
                    common metadata between many packages.
                    </para></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            Over time it became apparent that some further requirements
            were necessary:
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem><para>
                    Handle variants of a base recipe (e.g. native, sdk,
                    and multilib).
                    </para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>
                    Split metadata into layers and allow layers
                    to override each other.
                    </para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>
                    Allow representation of a given set of input variables
                    to a task as a checksum.
                    Based on that checksum, allow acceleration of builds
                    with prebuilt components.
                    </para></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            BitBake satisfies all the original requirements and many more
            with extensions being made to the basic functionality to
            reflect the additional requirements.
            Flexibility and power have always been the priorities.
            BitBake is highly extensible and supports embedded Python code and
            execution of any arbitrary tasks.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section id="Concepts">
        <title>Concepts</title>

        <para>
            BitBake is a program written in the Python language.
            At the highest level, BitBake interprets metadata, decides
            what tasks are required to run, and executes those tasks.
            Similar to GNU Make, BitBake controls how software is
            built.
            GNU Make achieves its control through "makefiles".
            BitBake uses "recipes".
        </para>

        <para>
            BitBake extends the capabilities of a simple
            tool like GNU Make by allowing for much more complex tasks
            to be completed, such as assembling entire embedded Linux
            distributions.
        </para>

        <para>
            The remainder of this section introduces several concepts
            that should be understood in order to better leverage
            the power of BitBake.
        </para>

        <section id='recipes'>
            <title>Recipes</title>

            <para>
                BitBake Recipes, which are denoted by the file extension
                <filename>.bb</filename>, are the most basic metadata files.
                These recipe files provide BitBake with the following:
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem><para>Descriptive information about the package</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>The version of the recipe</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Existing Dependencies</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Where the source code resides</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Whether the source code requires any patches</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>How to compile the source code</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>Where on the target machine to install the
                        package being compiled</para></listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>

            <para>
                Within the context of BitBake, or any project utilizing BitBake
                as it's build system, files with the <filename>.bb</filename>
                extension are referred to as recipes.
                <note>
                    The term "package" is also commonly used to describe recipes.
                    However, since the same word is used to describe packaged
                    output from a project, it is best to maintain a single
                    descriptive term, "recipes".
                </note>
            </para>
        </section>

        <section id='configuration-files'>
            <title>Configuration Files</title>

            <para>
                Configuration files, which are denoted by the
                <filename>.conf</filename> extension, define
                various configuration variables that govern the project's build
                process.
                These files fall into several areas that define
                machine configuration options, distribution configuration
                options, compiler tuning options, general common
                configuration options, and user configuration options.
                The main configuration file is the sample
                <filename>bitbake.conf</filename> file, which is
                located within the BitBake source tree
                <filename>conf</filename> directory.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section id='classes'>
            <title>Classes</title>

            <para>
                Class files, which are denoted by the
                <filename>.bbclass</filename> extension, contain
                information that is useful to share between metadata files.
                The BitBake source tree currently comes with one class metadata file
                called <filename>base.bbclass</filename>.
                You can find this file in the
                <filename>classes</filename> directory.
                The <filename>base.bbclass</filename> is special since it
                is always included automatically for all recipes
                and classes.
                This class contains definitions for standard basic tasks such
                as fetching, unpacking, configuring (empty by default),
                compiling (runs any Makefile present), installing (empty by
                default) and packaging (empty by default).
                These tasks are often overridden or extended by other classes
                added during the project development process.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section id='layers'>
            <title>Layers</title>

            <para>
                Layers allow you to isolate different types of
                customizations from each other.
                While you might find it tempting to keep everything in one layer
                when working on a single project, the more modular you organize
                your metadata, the easier it is to cope with future changes.
            </para>

            <para>
                To illustrate how you can use layers to keep things modular,
                consider machine customizations.
                These types of customizations typically reside in a special layer,
                rather than a general layer, called a Board Specific Package (BSP) Layer.
                Furthermore, the machine customizations should be isolated from
                recipes and metadata that support a new GUI environment, for
                example.
                This situation gives you a couple of layers: one for the machine
                configurations and one for the GUI environment.
                It is important to understand, however, that the BSP layer can still
                make machine-specific additions to recipes within
                the GUI environment layer without polluting the GUI layer itself
                with those machine-specific changes.
                You can accomplish this through a recipe that is a BitBake append
                (<filename>.bbappend</filename>) file.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section id='append-bbappend-files'>
            <title>Append Files</title>

            <para>
                Append files, which are files that have the
                <filename>.bbappend</filename> file extension, add or
                extend build information to an existing
                recipe file.
            </para>

            <para>
                BitBake expects every append file to have a corresponding recipe file.
                Furthermore, the append file and corresponding recipe file
                must use the same root filename.
                The filenames can differ only in the file type suffix used
                (e.g. <filename>formfactor_0.0.bb</filename> and
                <filename>formfactor_0.0.bbappend</filename>).
            </para>

            <para>
                Information in append files overrides the information in the
                similarly-named recipe file.
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section id='obtaining-bitbake'>
        <title>Obtaining BitBake</title>

        <para>
            You can obtain BitBake several different ways:
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem><para><emphasis>Cloning BitBake:</emphasis>
                    Using Git to clone the BitBake source code repository
                    is the recommended method for obtaining BitBake.
                    Cloning the repository makes it easy to get bug fixes
                    and have access to stable branches and the master
                    branch.
                    Once you have cloned BitBake, you should use
                    the latest stable
                    branch for development since the master branch is for
                    BitBake development and might contain less stable changes.
                    </para>
                    <para>You usually need a version of BitBake
                    that matches the metadata you are using.
                    The metadata is generally backwards compatible but
                    not forward compatible.</para>
                    <para>Here is an example that clones the BitBake repository:
                    <literallayout class='monospaced'>
     $ git clone git://git.openembedded.org/bitbake
                    </literallayout>
                    This command clones the BitBake Git repository into a
                    directory called <filename>bitbake</filename>.
                    Alternatively, you can
                    designate a directory after the
                    <filename>git clone</filename> command
                    if you want to call the new directory something
                    other than <filename>bitbake</filename>.
                    Here is an example that names the directory
                    <filename>bbdev</filename>:
                    <literallayout class='monospaced'>
     $ git clone git://git.openembedded.org/bitbake bbdev
                    </literallayout></para></listitem>
                <listitem><para><emphasis>Installation using your Distribution
                    Package Management System:</emphasis>
                    This method is not
                    recommended because the BitBake version that is
                    provided by your distribution, in most cases,
                    is several
                    releases behind a snapshot of the BitBake repository.
                    </para></listitem>
                <listitem><para><emphasis>Taking a snapshot of BitBake:</emphasis>
                    Downloading a snapshot of BitBake from the
                    source code repository gives you access to a known
                    branch or release of BitBake.</para>
                    <para>The following example downloads a snapshot of
                    BitBake version 1.17.0:
                    <literallayout class='monospaced'>
     $ wget http://git.openembedded.org/bitbake/snapshot/bitbake-1.17.0.tar.gz
     $ tar zxpvf bitbake-1.17.0.tar.gz
                    </literallayout>
                    After extraction of the tarball using the tar utility,
                    you have a directory entitled
                    <filename>bitbake-1.17.0</filename>.
                    </para></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
    </section>
</chapter>
